<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Global freshwater biodiversity research</title>
    <link>/authors/admin/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Global freshwater biodiversity research</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Sami Domisch {year}</copyright>
    
	    <atom:link href="/authors/admin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/authors/admin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/admin/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Sami Domisch is a Leibniz Junior Research Group Leader at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.igb-berlin.de/en/profile/sami-domisch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Leibniz-Institute of Freshwater Ecology and Inland Fisheries (IGB)&lt;/a&gt;. Sami is interested in freshwater biodiversity with an emphasis on spatial biodiversity patterns, macroecology, and developing tools to assess freshwater biodiversity across large spatial scales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group uses a wide array of open-source tools for spatial biodiversity informatics such as R, GRASS, GDAL/OGR, pktools, OpenForis within the Linux environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;career-br&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Career&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;since 2019 - Leibniz-Junior Research Group Leader at Leibniz-Institute of Freshwater Ecology and Inland Fisheries &lt;br/&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016-2019 - Leibniz-Institute of Freshwater Ecology and Inland Fisheries (Postdoc)  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2013-2016 - Yale University, USA (Postdoctoral associate and DFG postdoctoral fellow)  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2012-2013 - Biodiversity and Climate Research Centre (BiK-F), Frankfurt, Germany (Postdoc)  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;funding-and-awards-br&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding and awards&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leibniz Association and IGB: Leibniz Junior Research Group &amp;ldquo;Global freshwater biodiversity, biogeography and conservation (GLOWABIO)&amp;rdquo; (J45/2018), started in May 2019 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;German Research Foundation (DFG): Co-PI for grant &amp;lsquo;Himalopsyche/QTP Region&amp;rsquo; (DO 1880_3-2) &lt;br/&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF): Co-authored the proposal for grant &amp;lsquo;WANDEL&amp;rsquo; (GROW-937-3583-018; Co-PIs: S. Jähnig, M. Pusch)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;German Research Foundation (DFG): 2-year Postdoctoral fellowship at Yale University, USA (DO 1880_1-1) &lt;br/&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;EFFS-Award, subsidiary price for the best European PhD dissertation in freshwater science 2011-2012 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;reviewer-activities-br&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reviewer activities&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Member of Editorial Advisory Board: &lt;em&gt;Limnologica, Global Change Biology (2014-2017)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Funding agency: Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC) &lt;br/&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Journal referee: &lt;em&gt;Ecological Indicators, Biology Letters, Biological Invasions, Integrative Zoology, Biological Conservation, Methods in Ecology &amp;amp; Evolution, Ecological Engineering, Nature Scientific Reports, PLoS ONE, Ecography, Ecological Applications, Limnetica, Limnologica - Ecology and Management of Inland Waters, Global Ecology and Conservation, Naturwissenschaften, Marine Ecology Progress Series, Journal of Applied Ecology, Freshwater Biology, Journal of Environmental Management, Knowledge and Management of Aquatic Ecosystems, Journal of Biogeography, Hydrobiologia, Aquatic Sciences, Ecological Modelling, Freshwater Science, Diversity and Distributions, Global Ecology and Biogeography, Fundamental and Applied Limnology (Guest Editor), Global Change Biology (Advisory Board member 2013-2017)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/authors/author2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/author2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;test&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
