<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dr. Sami Domisch | Global freshwater biodiversity research</title>
    <link>/authors/admin/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/admin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Dr. Sami Domisch</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/authors/admin/avatar_hu07165238e7dcc72c98d15d70bd18f0fb_32119_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>Dr. Sami Domisch</title>
      <link>/authors/admin/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Freshwater biodiversity patterns</title>
      <link>/project/glowabio_biodiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/glowabio_biodiversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Global biodiversity is declining rapidly worldwide, and among terrestrial, marine and freshwater ecosystems, freshwaters are particularly vulnerable. These fragmented ecosystems cover less than 1% of the Earth’s surface, yet they harbour approximately 10% of all described species.
Aquatic insects contribute to freshwater diversity by approximately 60% as the largest and most diverse taxa group, and given this substantial proportion, aquatic insects may be considered as a proxy for freshwater biodiversity and ecological state of a given habitat.
We will use latest methods in species distribution modelling and spatial biodiversity science to analyze diversity patterns of this taxa group across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have collated, together with nearly 100 co-authors, a global database of Ephemeroptera, Plecoptera, Trichoptera and Odatanata (EPTO) occurrences comprising more than 8 million records. The data can be downloaded &lt;a href=&#34;https://fred.igb-berlin.de/data/package/725&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and visualized &lt;a href=&#34;https://geo.igb-berlin.de/maps/562/view&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://geo.igb-berlin.de/maps/562/view&#34; min-width : 900px ; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;EPTO database&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below we show a summary of the database: the number of observation records (a) and genera (b) for all orders, aggregated in a 10 km regular grid.  Number of observation records (c) and genera (d) for all orders per drainage basin. Number of observation records (e) and genera (f) per drainage basin for each order individually.
E: Ephemeroptera, P: Plecoptera, T: Trichoptera, O: Odonata. White and grey areas lack information.
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&amp;amp;ldquo;Fig. 1&amp;amp;rdquo;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/EPTO_Fig1_huba033007e31876f418732d2706fb7bc1_547895_de5cbe0d3c75243b5de60c33e3bb1a5a.webp 400w,
               /media/EPTO_Fig1_huba033007e31876f418732d2706fb7bc1_547895_71d63037faa7ea8cb82331c729397562.webp 760w,
               /media/EPTO_Fig1_huba033007e31876f418732d2706fb7bc1_547895_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/media/EPTO_Fig1_huba033007e31876f418732d2706fb7bc1_547895_de5cbe0d3c75243b5de60c33e3bb1a5a.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;614&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Freshwater habitat regionalization</title>
      <link>/project/glowabio_habitats/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/glowabio_habitats/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A first step towards global freshwater biodiversity assessments is a comprehensive quantification of the variety of habitat types. We aim to characterize the variety and distribution of global freshwater habitats at a high spatial resolution, to perfrom a regionalization analysis, and to provide environmental correlates of spatial biodiversity patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High-resolution hydrography</title>
      <link>/project/glowabio_hydrography/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/glowabio_hydrography/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Hydography90m&lt;/strong&gt; dataset&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used the MERIT Hydro Digital Elevation Model at 3 arc-sec (∼90 m at the equator) to derive a globally seamless, standardised hydrographic network, the &amp;ldquo;Hydrography90m&amp;rdquo;, with corresponding stream topographic and topologicalinformation. A central feature of the network is the minimal upstream contributing area, i.e. flow accumulation,of 0.05 km2 (or 5 ha) to initiate a stream channel, which allowed us to extract headwater stream channels ingreat detail. By employing a suite of GRASS GIS hydrological modules, we calculated the range-wide upstreamflow accumulation and flow direction to delineate a total of 1.6 million drainage basins, and extracted globallya total of 726 million unique stream segments with their corresponding sub-catchments. In addition, we computed stream topographic variables comprising stream slope, gradient, length, and curvature attributes, as wellas stream topological variables to allow for network routing and various stream order classifications. We validated the spatial accuracy and flow accumulation of Hydrography90m against NHDPlus HR, an independent,national high-resolution hydrographic network dataset of the United States. Our validation shows that the newly developed Hydrography90m has the highest spatial precision, and contains more headwater stream channels compared to three other global hydrographic datasets. This inclusive approach provides a vital, and long-overdue baseline for assessing actual streamflow in headwaters, and opens new research avenues for high-resolution studies of surface water worldwide. Hydrography90m thus offers significant potential to facilitate the assessment offreshwater quantity and quality, inundation risk, biodiversity and conservation, as well as resource managementobjectives in a globally comprehensive and standardised manner. We provide all the computed layers for visualisation and download in 20° × 20° tiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the pre-print at &lt;a href=&#34;https://essd.copernicus.org/preprints/essd-2022-9/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Earth System Science Data&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The data can be downloaded &lt;a href=&#34;https://public.igb-berlin.de/index.php/s/agciopgzXjWswF4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and visualized &lt;a href=&#34;https://essd.copernicus.org/preprints/essd-2022-9/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://geo.igb-berlin.de/maps/351/view&#34; min-width : 900px ; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;Hydrography90m&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Protected areas in Cuba</title>
      <link>/project/cuba_biodiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/cuba_biodiversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Freshwater ecosystems are among the most biodiverse and the most important providers of services to humans globally. Unfortunately, these ecosystems are also among the most threatened in the world. In Cuba, the main threats to freshwater ecosystems are climate change and habitat loss and fragmentation induced by land use/land cover change (LULC). Cuba’s National System of Protected Areas (in short SNAP for Sistema Nacional de Áreas Protegidas) is the main tool to protect biodiversity across the country. However, SNAP was not explicitly designed to account for freshwater biodiversity, ecosystem services, river’s connectivity and future scenarios of climate and LULC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main goal of the present project is to assess the protection offered by SNAP to freshwater biodiversity and to the provision of freshwater ecosystem services, considering the present conditions and future climate and land use/land cover change scenarios across Cuba. We expect to identify a hypothetical network of protected areas that should assure targets for biodiversity and ecosystem services in the present and future environmental conditions, at the lowest possible cost.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
