<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>admin on Global freshwater biodiversity research</title>
    <link>/authors/admin/</link>
    <description>Recent content in admin on Global freshwater biodiversity research</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Sami Domisch {year}</copyright>
    
	<atom:link href="/authors/admin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/author/admin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/author/admin/</guid>
      <description>Sami Domisch is a Leibniz Junior Research Group Leader at the Leibniz-Institute of Freshwater Ecology and Inland Fisheries (IGB). Sami is interested in freshwater biodiversity with an emphasis on spatial biodiversity patterns, macroecology, and developing tools to assess freshwater biodiversity across large spatial scales.
The group uses a wide array of open-source tools for spatial biodiversity informatics such as R, GRASS, GDAL/OGR, pktools, OpenForis within the Linux environment.
Career   since 2019 - Leibniz-Junior Research Group Leader at Leibniz-Institute of Freshwater Ecology and Inland Fisheries  2016-2019 - Leibniz-Institute of Freshwater Ecology and Inland Fisheries (Postdoc)  2013-2016 - Yale University, USA (Postdoctoral associate and DFG postdoctoral fellow)  2012-2013 - Biodiversity and Climate Research Centre (BiK-F), Frankfurt, Germany (Postdoc)   Funding and awards   Leibniz Association and IGB: Leibniz Junior Research Group &amp;ldquo;Global freshwater biodiversity, biogeography and conservation (GLOWABIO)&amp;rdquo; (J45/2018), started in May 2019  German Research Foundation (DFG): Co-PI for grant &amp;lsquo;Himalopsyche/QTP Region&amp;rsquo; (DO 1880_3-2)  Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF): Co-authored the proposal for grant &amp;lsquo;WANDEL&amp;rsquo; (GROW-937-3583-018; Co-PIs: S.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/author/author2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/author/author2/</guid>
      <description>test&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>